James, Henry, 1843-1916. Henry James letters to various correspondents and other material, 1861-1915 (MS Am 1094.1): Guide.
Henry James letters to various correspondents and other material,
- I. Letters from Henry James to others
  - 4 letters to George Abbott James,1872-1914 and undated., (151); 1 folder.
    Many of these previously undated.
    Includes letters: Rye, 1914 Sept. 13; Cambridge, [1872] May 8; Cambridge, [1875] Oct. 13; and Lowland House, Nahant, [1911 June-July].
    Also includes: 4 clippings; 3 reviews of Guy Domville from 1895 January; and 1 review of James "Theatricals", published 1897?
  - 4 letters to George Abbott James,1869-1911 and undated., (152); 1 folder.
    Letters previously undated.
    Includes letters: Intervale, [1911] July 4; no place, undated; Cambridge; and London, [1869] Mar 20.
  - 3 letters to George Abbott James, undated., (153); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Lenox, undated; no place, undated; and Rye, undated, with photograph of Garden Room on verso.
  - 1 letter to [Mrs. George Abbott] James; [Boston],[1883] Thursday., (154); 1 folder.
    58M-215 (60).
  - 1 letter to [Henry James 3rd]; Rye,[1912?]., (155); 1 folder.
    With typescript transcript of this letter. 50M-427.
  - 2 letters to William James?,1900-1908., (156); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, 1900 Nov. 11; and [ Paris ], 1908 May 3.
    54M-69 (1-2).
  - 1 letter to William James Jr.; Rye,1906 Dec. 7., (157); 1 folder.
    54M-71.
  - 5 letters to Rudyard Kipling,1899-1915., (158); 1 folder.
    1901 letter is a typescript transcript copy.
    66M-165.
  - 4 letters to Eleanor (Emmet) Lapsley,1902., (159); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: [ London ], 1902 July 15; Rye, Sussex, 1902 Aug. 8; Rye, Sussex, 1902 Sept. 16; and Rye, Sussex, 1902 Nov. 19.
    45M-347.
  - 4 letters to Eleanor (Emmet) Lapsley,1902-1903., (160); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, Sussex, 1902 Nov. 29; Rye, Sussex, 1903 June 30; Rye, Sussex, 1903 July 10; and Rye, Sussex, 1903 Oct. 2.
  - 3 letters to Eleanor (Emmet) Lapsley,1903-1904., (161); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, Sussex, 1903 Sept. 9; [ London ], 1904 Mar. 31; and Rye, Sussex, 1904 July 4.
  - 4 letters to Eleanor (Emmet) Lapsley,[1904]-1909., (162); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: [ London, 1904 July 12] this letter also to her husband John? Lapsley; Cambridge, Mass., 1905 Feb. 27; St. Louis, 1905 Mar. 6; and Rye, 1909 July 25.
  - 3 letters to Eleanor (Emmet) Lapsley,1911-1914., (163); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Cambridge, 1911 Feb. 23; [ New York], 1911 Mar. 31; and [ London], 1914 June 24.
  - 1 letter to [Mrs. ] Leslie; Rye,1914 Sept. 22., (164); 1 folder.
    58M-49.
  - 1 letter to Linton; [London], [ 1882 ] July 1., (165); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to [Col.] Lloyd; [London],1915 Oct. 27., (166); 1 folder.
    Requesting an extension of leave for Private Burgess Noakes. 53M-33.
  - 1 letter to Louisa [Loring]; Rye, Sussex,1903 Sept. 22., (167); 1 folder.
    47M-4.
  - 9 typescript transcript letters to Louisa Loring and Katherine Loring,1910, and undated., (168); 1 folder.
    Originals in Beverly Historical Society.
    Received: 1947.
  - 1 photostat letter to [Sir Frederick?] Macmillan; Paris,[1885] Sept. 15., (169); 1 folder.
    Original in the Benjamin Ticknor Papers in the Library of Congress..
    43M-413F.
  - 1 letter to [Silas] Weir Mitchell; Rome,1899 May 14., (170); 1 folder.
    43M-2.
  - 1 letter to Burgess Noakes; Rye,1914 Sept. 8., (171); 1 folder.
    53M-32.
  - 1 letter to Burgess Noakes; [London],1915 Mar. 22., (172); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Burgess Noakes; [London],1915 May 25., (173); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Burgess Noakes; [London],1915 June 1., (174); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Burgess Noakes; [London],1915 June 13., (175); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Burgess Noakes; [London],1915 July 17., (176); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Burgess Noakes; [London],1915 Sept. 29., (177); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Burgess Noakes;, [London],1915 Oct. 2., (178); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Burgess Noakes;, [London],1915 Oct. 8., (179); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Charles Eliot Norton; [London],1896 Sept. 11., (180); 1 folder.
  - 5 letters to Eliot Norton,1895-1911., (181); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Torquay, 1895 Sept. 9; Rye, 1899 Sept 6; Cambridge, 1904 Oct. 7; Rye, 1911 Jan. 2; and [London], 1887 July 21.
    Purchased with funds from the Norton Fund, 1933 Sept. 18.
  - 1 letter to Grace Norton; Rye, Sussex, [ 1886 ]., (182); 1 folder.
    Signature torn away. 49M- [sic].
  - 5 letters to Richard Norton,1899-1914., (183); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Naples, 1899 June 17; [London], 1913 Feb. 23; [London]; 1913 June 5; Rye, 1914 Sept. 19; and [London] 1914 Nov. 23.
  - 1 letter to J[ames] R[ipley] Osgood; London,[1877] Feb. 8., (183a); 1 folder.
    2003M-61.
  - 1 letter to J[ames] R[ipley] Osgood; Cambridge (Mass.),1883 Jan. 1., (183b); 1 folder.
  - 1 photostat letter to [James R.] Osgood; [Boston],1883 Apr. 8., (184); 1 folder.
    Original in the Benjamin Ticknor Papers in the Library of Congress.
    43M-411F.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,, 1903-1904., (185); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: [London], 1903 May 18; [London], 1903 July 18; [London], 1904 Mar. 3; [London], 1904 Mar. 21; and Chocorua, NH., 1904 Sept. 6.
    45M-57F.
  - 4 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1905-1906., (186); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Los Angeles, 1905 Mar. 25; Rye, Sussex, 1905 Nov. 22; Rye, Sussex, 1906 Jan. 9; and Rye, Sussex, 1906 Nov. 27.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1907-1908., (187); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, Sussex, 1907 Jan. 22; Rye, Sussex, 1908 Jan. 21; Rye, Sussex, 1908 Mar. 6, completed by fragment in item (201); [London], 1908 June 19; and Rye, Sussex, 1908 Aug. 21.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1908-1910., (188); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, Sussex, 1908 Sept. 16; Rye, Sussex, 1909 July 29; Rye, Sussex, 1910 Apr. 28; [London], 1910 July 19; and Rye, Sussex, [no year] Nov. 4.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1911-1912 and undated., (189); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, Sussex, 1911 Oct. 4; [London], 1911 Oct. 18; [London], 1912 Apr. 30; Rye, Sussex, undated; and Rye, Sussex, undated.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persee, undated., (190); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, Sussex; [London]; [no place]; [London]; and [London], July 14.
  - 1 letter to Jocelyn Persse; [London],1906 Nov. 4., (191); 1 folder.
    Fragment only that completes item (195), letter 5.
  - Typescript transcripts of above letters to Jocelyn Persse.1903-1912 and undated., (192); 1 folder.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1903-1905., (193); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, Sussex, 1903 July 21; Rye, Sussex, 1903 Dept. 15; Rye, Sussex, 1904 Aug. 10; Rye, Sussex, 1905 Aug. 24; and Rye, Sussex, 1905 Sept. 21.
    46M-89F.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1905-1906., (194); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: [London], 1905 Oct. 24; Rye, Sussex, 1905 Nov. 6; Rye, Sussex, 1906 Feb. 2; [London], 1906 Feb. 13.; and [London], 1906 Apr. 4.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1906., (195); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, Sussex, 1906 June 17; Rye, Sussex, 1906 Sept. 13; Rye, Sussex, 1906 Oct. 10; Rye, Sussex, 1906 Oct. 28; and [London], 1906 Nov. 4, letter completed by fragment in item (191).
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1907-1908., (196); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Paris, 1907 May 4; Rye, Sussex, 1907 Dec. 9; Rye, Sussex, 1907 Dec. 12; Rye, Sussex, 1908 Jan. 30; and Rye Sussex, 1908 Feb. 22.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1908-1910., (197); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, Sussex, 1908 July 9; [London] 1909 July 4; Rye, Sussex, 1909 July 16; Rye, Sussex, 1909 Nov. 5; and Cambridge, Mass., 1910 Oct. 27.
  - 5 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1911-1914., (198); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: [London], 1911 Dec. 2; Rye, Sussex, 1912 Oct. 28; Rye, Sussex, 1914 Aug. 11; [London], 1914 Oct. 8; [London], 1914 Nov. 15.
  - 4 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1914 and undated., (199); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: [London], 1914 Nov. 16; [London], undated; Rye, Sussex, undated; and [London], undated.
    Also with 1 letter from (Captain) Dacre to Vincent about J. Persse, Rye, Sussex, undated.
  - 4 letters to Jocelyn Persse, undated., (200); 1 folder.
    Includes fragments of letters all from Rye, Sussex.
  - 4 letters to Jocelyn Persse,1908 Mar. 6 and undated., (201); 1 folder.
    Includes fragments of letters from: Rye, Sussex, 1908 Mar. 6 which completes item (187); Lenox, Mass., and no place.
  - 1 letter to Jocelyn [Persse]; Rye,1903 Oct. 23., (202); 1 folder.
    58M-50.
  - 1 letter to Jocelyn [Persse]; Rye,1908 Oct. 22., (203); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Jocelyn [Persse]; [London],1912 May 31., (204); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Jocelyn [Persse]; [London, undated]., (205); 1 folder.
  - 4 letters to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie;1890-1897., (206); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, [1890] Aug. 16; [London], 1895 Apr. 9; Bournemouth, [1897] June 30; and [London] [ca. 1898] Aug. 16.
    Gift of Mrs. Hester R. Fuller. 50M-15.
  - 5 letters to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie;1899-1905., (207); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, 1899 Sept. 2; Rye, 1899 Sept. 2; Rye, 1903 Nov. 5; Rye, 1904 Sept. 25; and [London] 1905 Oct. 27.
    50M-15.
  - 5 letters to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie;1906-1914 and undated., (208); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Rye, 1906 Nov. 12; Rye, 1910 Feb. 14; [London], 1912 Feb. 16; [London], 1914 June 30; and [London], undated.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London],1900 Jan. 4., (209); 1 folder.
    54M-67.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; Rye,1902 Dec. 31., (210); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; Rye,1903 Nov. 19., (211); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; Rye,1904 Aug. 15., (212); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London],1906 Dec. 21., (213); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London],1908 June 1., (214); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London],1908 Dec. 3., (215); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; Cambridge, Mass.,1910 Oct. 30., (216); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London],1913 Mar. 25., (217); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London],1913 Dec. 16., (218); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London],1914 May 6., (219); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London],1915 May 30., (220); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London],1915 Aug. 11., (221); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London], undated., (222); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to Lady Anne Isabella (Thackeray) Ritchie; [London], undated., (223); 1 folder.
  - 1 letter to [Mrs. ] Robinson; Cambridge,1905 June 25., (224); 1 folder.
    No date or source.
  - 1 letter to Scribners; Rye,1906 June 28., (225); 1 folder.
    Purchased with royalties, 1963 Feb. 12.
  - 4 letters to Horace Elisha Scudder,1890., (226); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: [London], 1890 Aug. 30; [London], 1890 Oct. 5; [London], [1890] Oct. 27; and [London], [1890] Nov. 10.
    58M-173.
  - 4 letters to Horace Elisha Scudder,1891., (227); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Paris, 1891 Mar. 4; [London], [1891] May 27; [London], [1891] May 30; and Kingstown, Ireland, 1891 July 18.
  - 4 letters to Horace Elisha Scudder,1891., (228); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Kingstown, [1891] July 22; Kingstown, 1891 Aug. 1; [London], [1891] Sept. 10; and [London], 1891 Oct. 21.
  - 4 letters to Horace Elisha Scudder,1891-1895., (229); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: [London], 1891 Nov. 11, [London], 1895 May 12; [London], 1895 June 8; and [London], 1895 Sept. 3.
  - 4 letters to Horace Elisha Scudder,1895., (230); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: Torquay, 1895 Oct. 4; Torquay, 1895 Oct. 10; [London], 1895 Nov. 6; and [London], 1895 Nov. 9.
  - 5 letters to Horace Elisha Scudder,1895-1896., (231); 1 folder.
    Includes letters: [London], 1895 Dec. 18; [London], [1896 Feb.]; [London], 1896 Mar. 3; [London], 1896 Mar. 24; and Playden, 1896 May 21.
  - 1 letter to Clare (Frewen) Sheridan; Rye, Sussex,1911 Oct. 22., (232); 1 folder.
    51M-104.
  - 1 letter to [Miss Edith] Sichel; Lamb House,1909 Dec. 28., (233); 1 folder.
    65M-30.
  - 1 letter to Edward Fordham Spence; [London],1895 Jan. 8., (234); 1 folder.
    46M-84A.
  - 1 letter to [Robert Louis] Stevenson; [London,1893]., (235); 1 folder.
    First 4 pages of letter missing.
    Regrets having missed R.L.S.'s mother during her recent London visit; has been out of England; thanks for presenting him with Island Nights; praises "Beach of Falesa" especially; hopes "David Balfour" will soon be out as a book; refers civilized to primitive men unless R.L.S. writes about the latter.
    42M-161.
  - 3 letters to Frederic Murray Stimson,1899-1911., (236); 1 folder.
    65M-130.
  - 1 letter to Frederick Sturges; Chocorua, N.H.,1904 Sept. 4., (237); 1 folder.
    With typescript transcript and T.L.s. from F.S. to Henry James, nephew of the novelist, with env.
  - 1 letter to [Dame Ellen] Terry; [London],1895 Apr. 23., (238); 1 folder.
    Requesting an appointment to discuss a one-act play.
    49M-102.
  - 1 letter photostat to [Benjamin] Ticknor; [London],1883 Sept. 10., (239); 1 folder.
    43M-412F.
  - 1 letter photostat to [Benjamin] Ticknor; [London],[1885] June 26., (240); 1 folder.
    43M-415F.
  - 1 letter photostat to [Benjamin] Ticknor,1885., (241); 1 folder.
    43M-414.
  - 1 letter photostat to [Benjamin] Ticknor; [London],[188-?] Dec. 22., (242); 1 folder.
    43M-416F.
  - 1 letter to Ticknor and Fields; Jefferson (N.H.), ca. 1866-1868 July 26., (242a); 1 folder.
    2009M-61.
  - 1 letter to Messrs. Welch and Bigelow; New York, undated., (243); 1 folder.
    Recataloged from the autograph file.
  - 1 letter to Garnet Joseph Wolseley, 1st viscount Wolseley; Rye, Sussex,1903 Dec. 7., (244); 1 folder.
    Discussed Wolseley's recently published The story of a soldier's life. Apparently unpublished.
    45M-169F.
  - 1 letter to [ ] Woollett; [London],[189-?] May 22., (245); 1 folder.
    44M-147.
  - 1 letter to Wyckoff; Lenox, Mass.,1904 Oct 22., (246); 1 folder.
    49M-42.
  - 1 letter to unidentified correspondent, 1861 Sept. 9., (247); 1 folder.
    68M-132.
- II. Other material
  - Edel, Leon, 1907-. 1 letter to Carolyn Elizabeth Jakeman; Jamaica, New York,1952 Dec. 6., (248); 1 folder.
    Concerns a Henry James letter.
    69M-148 (1).
  - 9 photographs of Henry James and friends; Newington House,1909., (249); 1 folder.
    Taken from the guest book for 1905-1911 of Newington House.
    James Pope Hennessy, 1972 Apr.